All right.
In this lecture
we're going to talk about Kubernetes
scheduling, which, takes advantage.
The autoscaler take advantage
of this Kubernetes scheduling.
So it's important to understand
how this core concept, and the idea here
is that the scheduler is assigning
individual pods to nodes.
So that's, that's its main thing.
And it's all based off of resources,
constraints and policies
that you can establish with the end
goal of optimizing utilization,
performance or replacement
needs as, based off of the policies
that you establish.
So understanding
how this works can be very beneficial
if you're using any of the auto
scalers or,
or if you want to understand
how to best optimize
your cluster for the types of workloads
that you're dealing with.
So the scheduling flow
is, very straightforward here.
I've got
a watch API that's looking at pods.
I'm seeing if I have in any empty pods,
or I pods that haven't been scheduled yet.
I go through some filtering, predicates
to give me a list
of nodes that I can run these
on based off of the pod requirements.
And then are there
any feasible nodes out there?
If the answer is yes,
then it's going to prioritize,
where to put, those nodes best
based off of lots of different scheduling.
Parameters that you can establish
whether least requested
balance node affinities, taint, toleration
custom plugins.
There's lots of different things
that I can do here.
And then whatever has
the highest, score gets picked.
I drop that pod on that node
and I'm off to the races.
If there aren't any
feasible nodes,
then I need to look and see.
Do I have any pods
that are leaving a node?
If there are, then I'm.
I have the opportunity to retry
and see if I can,
have an event, been out to have a new node
if I can,
or I have to sit and wait
and wait for some pods to evacuate.
The current nodes that I currently have,
and in that case, I can get,
starvation of, requests
that are coming in.
So you have to be mindful of that,
of those sorts of things.
Okay.
So you gotta watch for,
unassigned pods because it means
that your stuff will never run.
And that could be very problematic
if your stuff isn't going to run.
So you need to make sure that,
your scheduler is watching
the API server for pods
whose node name is unset.
That's how you can find out
when you're going in, you're trying
to figure out what's going on.
Okay.
Let's talk about filtering real quick.
So I've got a pending pod out there
and it has its requirements in there.
Request.
It can say how much
how much memory do I need.
How much CPU cycles do
I think I'm going to take?
I can have a node selector saying,
I want to run in this certain zone
over here.
I have a port address
that I need available to me.
Lots of different things that I could
put into that pending Pod request.
Then it runs to the predicates and finds
all the nodes that I have
and says filters out which nodes
are candidates for that, and then it will.
After it does all of that, it will then
start to score the nodes that are left.
If you're too tight on your constraints,
you can,
starve these pods from being spun up,
in a highly
contested or highly utilized, cluster.
So you got to be careful
of those sorts of things.
So here are some of the details
that, you can use when filtering.
Just be mindful if you, if you have it
too tight and too narrow, higher
likelihood you're not going to be able
to pick a node for that pot.
So be careful of that.
So, there's resource bits like CPU, memory
storage things, things like that.
I've got pod fit port, so,
ports that I need,
if the ports are already used,
I can't use that pod, for example.
So you got to be careful of that.
There's node selector where I can,
select specific nodes by name
or by region.
I've got, toleration for hey,
it didn't quite fit,
but I have some slack here
that I can play around with.
I have some affinity and anti
infinity rules
that I can establish
where I've got these two pods.
They need to run close to each other
type of thing
or anti anti affinity rules
saying I don't care where they run.
They can run wherever because I don't care
about latency between things.
So take a look at all
these different filter filters
when you're creating
your pod resource requirements
okay.
Scoring a scoring is important as well.
And I can base those scoring
after different functions
like the least requested node.
I want it balanced.
I have that affinity, thing there.
Toleration.
And I can do custom, custom plugins.
Custom plugins can tie into things like,
Prometheus
or Grafana to get metrics out.
And I can even have applications that have
specific metrics that they're producing.
You could put anything in that plugin
that helps, generate a score.
The idea here is the highest score wins.
So whatever you want in your scheduler,
that highest score selects the right node
based off of that score and goes, okay,
I'm going to select in this case
no D because it had the highest score
that I calculated.
So that's the whole idea of the scheduler.
All right.
Scoring details.
We already kind of touched
a little on this.
The idea is to find the best node
for the pod that you're going to run.
So the pod itself needs to describe
what it's going to do
and kind of, helps with the scoring.
Right?
So I can I can score without knowing
anything that the pod wants to do.
But that's kind of blind scoring.
I, a round robin
does a lot of that sort of thing.
Like least requested.
All right. I'll run that or balance.
That's round robin node affinity
means I do know something about what
the pod wants.
It's going to favor
certain nodes based off of the criteria
that are established in the pod itself.
And I can penalize pods if they
if they have something that I don't need,
I can take that off.
Off the table.
Custom plugin scores
I can use to help identify
maybe specific CPUs
that have certain accelerators in them,
or maybe an FPGA
that is attached to a certain,
CPU or
certain machine or a GPU
or things like that.
I can use custom plugins scores and,
and some other techniques
that are out there today.
But the idea here
is that these scoring mechanisms
can help identify the best,
the best as defined by the scoring details
part.
Node for the pod
that you're trying to schedule.
When I pick that node,
then I bind that pod to that node.
And the key here is that
if the binding fails,
the node becomes unscheduled or something.
Because there is a time that I take
that pod back up into the scheduler
at a higher priority,
because I've already scheduled it once.
I need to put it in front of the queue
for scheduling
because I've already established,
a need for it.
And if I can't find a need,
then it goes back into the queue.
So these retries
and evictions are very important
because things are very dynamic.
There could a lot of things happen
by the time I say schedule
this pod or bind this pod to this node
and the node being available.
So I have to take that into consideration.
All right.
Key concepts you
want to make sure that you understand here
is node capacity versus
allocate.
All right I could allocate
a pod there.
But the node may not have the capacity
to do it.
So those are two things.
There may be a case
where I can't allocate a pod
to a node for some other reasons.
It may have capacity,
but maybe it doesn't have the right
type of, hardware attached to it
or something like that.
So those are differences, right?
I've got a number of requests
that I have coming
in, and requests drive the scheduling.
The limits are limiting.
To that, I've got taints and tolerant,
and toleration.
A taint repels pods
from landing on a specific node.
And, toleration is
are are more flexibility
in a landing a pod on a node.
And then I've got that affinity
and anti affinity.
I want to co-locate pods on the same node
or separate them based off of the type of
resources that they need.
And also maybe for,
scalability and reliability.
I don't want to run all of my replicas
of my microservice on the same machine.
If I need it to be highly available,
because if that machine goes down,
I just lost all of them.
That was a great example.
Also,
I can and should look at topology spreads,
where I want to distribute my pods across
multiple nodes, across multiple zones,
as as the zones could be regions,
even if I wanted to.
And then take a look
at some of the, custom scheduling logic
that are out there.
There are lots of great
examples out there.
If you have something more complex
that you want to use
to schedule these pods to nodes.
All right.
Configuration and tuning.
There's lots of different options here.
Profiles can be used.
Where multiple
scheduler configs per workload.
So I can have different profiles,
development profile,
production profile, profile, test profile.
I can even have different production
profiles, that are established out there.
I've got
priorities, the concept of priorities.
Which pods have the highest priority?
A lot of these terms where, come from
the high performance computing schedule,
schedulers that are out there,
they use a lot of the same,
concepts and,
design patterns that are out there.
Everything from priorities, quotas
and limit ranges, affinities,
anti affinities, taints,
and those are all, things
you find in high performance computing.
Schedulers.
Okay.
Now comes
how in the world do you debug a scheduler?
Well,
the first thing you're going to know is
I schedule pod and it can't it can't run.
It's not running. Why is it not running?
So I want to be able to describe,
that pod that I asked to go out
so I can look at, and describe the pod
and it will tell me the reasons
why it's not running or where it got run.
I can also take a look at the logs of
the cube scheduler to see what's going on.
Hopefully the scheduler isn't
having issues communicating
to the nodes, and vice versa.
Or maybe my constraints are too too much.
My profiles have too many constraints
in them, or
my pod requests have too many constraints
and I can't hit anything.
So looking at,
your logs can tell you a lot of that stuff
and then make some, decisions
on your filter
and score that that you're looking at,
and make some adjustments
as you need to, and then make sure
that you're watching the metrics.
And, dashboards
to see what's really going on.
You could have some pods
that are running out of control
and microservice
that gets stuck in a, heaven forbid, a mal
like a fork while one loop, which
hopefully no one's ever written that.
I know some of you have.
I used to be a sysadmin,
and that has popped up where they consume
all the resources on a machine
and leave the machine basically unusable.
So find out what's going on
by using these different techniques.
I already mentioned
Kube describe pod
for looking at scheduling events.
Look at the scheduler logs and then try
to simulate scheduling decisions.
With a dry run, which you can easily do.
How when you, deploy a pod.
All right.
Best practices across the board here.
Set requests carefully.
Avoid over an under use affinity sparingly
because affinity can constrain it too much
leverage topology.
Spreads across zones to give you higher,
reliability and availability
and then monitor your pending pods.
If that list starts getting really large,
you could have some other things
that are going on.
You can also combine these autoscaler
with a cluster autoscaler,
which can add or this scheduler
with the cluster autoscaler
which can add additional nodes
to your cluster.
But be careful with that as well.
If you're running in a cloud
and you've got a disaster that's happening
and you tie it directly to your autoscaler
and it just keeps adding more and more
nodes and you're consuming all the nodes
because something's out of control.
You've got some funky while loop that's
spinning up pods and consuming resources.
You can blow through your,
cloud budget very quickly.
All right.
That's what a Kubernetes scheduler does.
Matches pods to nodes efficiently,
sometimes very efficiently.
If you have things wrong,
it will do it very efficiently
and keep driving something wrong.
Use filter
scores, affinities and priorities.
When establishing your profiles and your
your pod requirements that you have.
And remember,
the goal of this is high availability.
Cluster efficiency,
which means grow and shrink, right?
Don't
consume more resources than you need to.
We kind of get lazy when we're running
in our own data centers,
so be mindful of that
when you're running in the cloud,
because those resources cost money.